KIMANI P. GITHIRI JOHN

PO Box 47321 (00100) Nairobi Tel: +254710-880264 E mail: john_githiri@yahoo.co.uk

COMPETENCY HIGHLIGHTS

Professional Training - Master of Science in Occupational Safety and Health and has an International General Certificate in Occupational Safety and Health; a Masters in Business Administration (MBA) - Specializing in Strategic Management; and a Bachelor of Science (BSc) in Mechanical Engineering.

Experience

- Over 15 years of experience in progressive manufacturing and engineering management progressing into strategic roles in Quality, Environmental, Health and Safety management in international companies with global best practices;
- Has solid exposure in food manufacturing, engineering and assembly industries;
- Has hands on experience in developing, implementing and monitoring quality, health and safety systems,
- Has worked in a broad range of capacities in professional services delivery and line management;
- Has worked under structured change systems, competitive capacity management, performance oriented set ups with proven results

Technical Aptitude

- Process Management Process Mapping and identification of QEHS risks & implications;
- Systems Design Developing systems for environmental, quality, health and Safety
- Change Management Undertaking Change Readiness Capacity Assessments; Designing and Implementation of Change Management Strategic Framework; Conceptualisation and implementation of roll out plans for QEHS;
- QEHS Solutions Design and Implementation
- QEHS Analytics including Root Cause Analysis and Problem Solving

Career Achievements

- Developed QMS, EMS and OHSAS manuals for General Motors East Africa Limited, East Africa Maltings Limited, Kenya Breweries Limited and Central Glass Industries Limited, all subsidiaries of East African Breweries Limited (EABL) leading to certification to applicable international management system standards;
- Developed and implemented Contractor Safety Training program for EABL sites;
- Carried out task-based OSH risk assessments for all 3 EABL (Kenya) sites;
- Realised over 50% reduction in accident rate at KBL within 2 years of assignment leading to site being recognised as "most improved site" within Diageo in 2013;
- Managed project safety during the CGI full furnace rebuild with zero injuries this was a high value (Kshs 1 billion), high intensive project involving over 10 international contractors

WORKING EXPERIENCE

Manager - Safety, Health, Environment & Security at Consol Ltd (CGIL), Oct 2015 to date

Overview: Currently in this position at Central Glass Industries, a subsidiary of South African based Consol Glass Pty Limited.

Responsibilities

- Liaising with operations and production managers to ensure compliance with applicable corporate and local legal SHES standards.
- Providing SHES feedback, co-ordinating SHES problem resolution and monitoring improvement plans.
- Ensuring CGIL's SHES management systems are established, implemented and maintained in accordance with ISO14001 and OHSAS18001 international standards.
- Planning and executing SHES internal audits, NEMA environment self-audits and reporting to the management on a regular basis on performance of respective management systems.
- Serving as liaison with external parties on matters relating to CGIL's Safety and Environment Management Systems as the Management Representative.
- Manage operations of the contracted security service provider to assure personnel and asset security.

Manager - Safety, Health & Environment, East African Breweries Ltd, Nov '07 to Sept 2015

Overview: Held this position for a number of subsidiaries of the company including Central Glass Industries Ltd; Kenya Breweries Ltd and East Africa Maltings Ltd at different times within the period.

Responsibilities

- Liaising with operations and production managers to ensure compliance with applicable corporate and local legal EHS requirements.
- Providing EHS feedback, co-ordinating EHS problem resolution and monitoring improvement plans.
- Ensuring East African Breweries Ltd's EHS management systems are established, implemented and maintained in accordance with ISO14001 and OHSAS18001 international standards.
- Planning and executing EHS internal audits, NEMA environment self audits and reporting to the management on a regular basis on performance of respective management systems.
- Serving as liaison with external parties on matters relating to EABL's Environment and Safety Management Systems as the Management Representative.

Associate Management Systems Consultant/Trainer - Environment, Health and Safety Management Systems, Dataline International Ltd, Aug 2006 to date

Responsibilities

- Carrying out audits to establish the status of QEHS and advising management of client companies on what needs to be done;
- Designing solutions and training programmes to address the identified client needs;
- Delivering the required interventions to address the identified client gaps;
- Continually building the capacity of the company to handle quality risks;
- Reporting to the management on a regular basis on the performance of quality, environment, health and safety systems.

Manager - Quality, Environment Health & Safety, General Motors (EA) Ltd, Aug 1996 to Jul 2006

Responsibilities

- Liaising with Manufacturing, Product Development and Service managers to support assembly and vehicle service operations in order to ensure compliance with applicable vehicle specifications, quality standards and procedures;
- Providing quality feedback, co-ordinating quality problem resolution and monitoring quality improvement action plans;
- Ensuring GM East Africa Quality, Environment and Safety management systems are established, implemented and maintained in accordance with ISO 9001, ISO 14001 and OHSAS 18001 international standards.
- Planning and participating in actual internal audits of GM East Africa Quality, Environment and Safety management systems;
- Serving as liaison with external parties on matters relating to GM East Africa Quality,
 Environment and Safety Management Systems as the Management Representative;
- Reporting to the management on a regular basis on the performance of quality, environmental and safety systems;
- Establishing control and calibration programmes for inspection, measurement, setting, testing and torque tools, gauges or equipment relating to critical operations.

Other Positions Held in the company

- Plant Maintenance Supervisor, General Motors (EA) Ltd
- Production Engineer, General Motors (EA) Ltd

OTHER ROLES HELD

Mechanical Engineer, Metal Crowns Limited; May 1996 to Jun 1996

TRAINING AND CONSULTANCY EXPERIENCE

- Consultant, OHS Audit of Eastern Produce limited Nandi Hills, 2009 to date
- Trainer OHS Committee Training, PZ Cussons, Mashariki Motors, Aggreko Power Generators, Appex Apparels and Brush Manufacturers Ltd, Jul - Aug 2007
- Consultant, OHS Audit of Kakuzi limited Makuyu, 2007 to date
- Consultant, OHS Audit of Kenya Power limited, Gertrudes Hospital, Kenya Literature Bureau, Hi-plast limited, Cooper Kenya limited, World Vision International, Crop Africa limited – various dates from 2007 to date
- Consultant, Development of ISO 9001 QMS Implementation Manual for SMEs affiliated with FKE, May 2007
- Trainer, HR managers from various organisations KIM on OHS, May 2007
- Trainer OHS, Sunripe (1976) Limited's OHS Committees (JKIA and Naivasha), 2007
- Trainer OHS, New KCC limited's OHS Committees, Jan Mar 2007
- Trainer Environmental Internal Auditing, Toyota EA limited's EHS team, Oct 2006

PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

Professional Training

- Master of Science in Occupational Safety and Health, Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology, 2016
 - Thesis Title: "The Status of OSH and Effectiveness of Contractor Management Programs at Kenya Breweries Limited"
- International General Certificate in Occupational Safety and Health A NEBOSH assessed (UK) program, Rapid Results College (RRC) London, Sept 2009
- Masters in Business Administration (MBA) Specializing in Strategic Management, University of Nairobi, 2008
 - Thesis Title: "The Role of ISO9001 Certification in Developing Competitive Advantage for Kenyan Organizations"
- Bachelor of Science (BSc) in Mechanical Engineering, Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology, 1995

<u>Professional Membership</u>

- Registered Management Systems Auditor, Kenya Bureau of Standards Personnel Certification Scheme - No. KEBS/PC/18
- Registered Safety Advisor, Directorate of Occupational Health and Safety Services (DOHSS) - No. OSH/ADV 057
- Registered Fire Safety Auditor, Directorate of Occupational Health and Safety Services (DOHSS) - No. OSH/FSA 096
- Member, KEBS Technical Committees on Conformity Assessment, Ergonomics and Anthropometry

Short Training Undertaken

- OHSAS 18001 Lead Auditor Training, Bureau Veritas Nairobi, Mar 2009
- Fire Prevention & Protection workshop, Micas Limited EAML, Mar 2009
- Global Customer Audit Training, GM South Africa Port Elizabeth, Nov 2005
- Global Manufacturing Training, GM Egypt Plant Cairo, Egypt, Apr 2002
- Induction into Engineering Professionalism (ERB and IEK) seminar at JKUAT, Jun 1995

Seminars Attended

- ISO 14001:2015 Transition Seminar in Johannesburg South Africa, May 2016
- Diageo Contractors "Zero Harm" Safety Workshop, Safari Park Hotel, Feb 2014
- Stakeholder Workshop on Development of Asbestos Waste Management Regulations, NEMA, Aug 2012
- Diageo Safety Conference at St. James' Gate, Dublin, Ireland, Sept 2009
- Stakeholders' Workshop Masters Degree Curriculum Development in Environmental Science for University of Nairobi, Sept 2006
- Occupational Health & Safety Seminar, Current Occupational Environment & Health Agency- Norfolk Hotel, Jun 2005
- GM Global Environment Conference, GM Detroit, Michigan USA, Sep 2004
- Environment Awareness Workshop, NEMA Panafric Hotel, Dec 2003
- Peak Performance Strategies Seminar, KSPS Naromoru River Lodge, May 2002
- ISO 9000:2000 Transition Seminar, KEBS Grand Regency Hotel, Jun 2001
- Statistical Quality Control Seminar, KEBS Silver Springs Hotel, Jul 1999
- Participated in Assets Management Project, Kenya Shell & BP Co. Ltd, Jul 1996

Computer Knowledge

- AutoCAD 2000 (R12);
- Microsoft Office packages (Excel, Word, PowerPoint)

REFEREES

Cyprian Mungume; Depot Manager, Total Kenya Ltd; P O Box 30736, Nairobi;

Tel: +254733677070; E-mail: cyprian.mungume@total.co.ke

Emmanuel Ogot; **Engineering and Manufacturing Director, GMEA Ltd;** P O Box 30527 - 00100 Nairobi; Tel: +254733917456; E-mail: emmanuel.ogot@gm.com

Kioko Ndolo; **Certification Manager, SGS Kenya Ltd;** P O Box 72118 (00200) Nairobi; Tel: +254733637149; E-mail: kioko_ndolo@sgs.com

Beethoven Mathenge; **Managing Director, Dataline International Ltd;** P O Box 51573 (00200) Nairobi; Tel: +254 722385295; E-mail: benmathenge@dataline.co.ke